Date: Monday 27th Apr 2009

Time: 14:30-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08445805588

Pin: 70503011

Attending

Manchester: Jits, Franck, Steve

EBI: Eric, Thomas

Apologies

Carole, Rodrigo

Minuting

Franck

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

Report back from Biocuration meeting

SAB minutes?

Annotation model document

Possible collaboration with Microsoft

Plan for the BioIT meeting

Progress/developement of the pilot - are we rolling?

Report back from silent public release

Test infrastructure setup at EBI and progress of service testing/monitoring piece.

Technical meeting

Summary of tasks on Rubyforge

BioCatalogue support review

20 Questions analysis

Actions from Previous Meeting

Thomas, Franck: update the SAB minutes and make them more comprehensive minutes… ongoing

Carole: ring BBSRC programme manager to inform her that the SAB has taken place and then see what they have to say…completed

Eric: provide an update on what is happening with the test scripts execution environment…ongoing

Update on decision on the script running environment…ongoing

Investigate background processing for long running tasks… assigned to Jits

Re-prioritize work on the API for service monitoring… assigned to jits

Franck & Eric : Produce elaborate document on the BioCatalogue data model …ongoing: we've set up the outline of the document and writing it up.

All : Decide on how to go forward with the ratings [ on whether we make that available to the public at this stage or not] … ongoing

Minutes

Testing environment at the EBI

The EBI wants a explicit document of the type of the test we'll harvest,

Service monitoring

We questioned the use of the traffic light system for the monitor piece only. Pinging a service endpoint and not getting a response back does not necessarily mean that the service is dead (i.e DDBJ). Other criteria such as host name, wsdl availability may also be misleading. We(Eric, Franck, Jits and Thomas) think that the traffic light system should be the result of a careful test (with tests scripts provided by service providers). There is therefore a need to find other ways to present(interface wise) the result of a monitored service. Or the traffic light system could be the result of service monitoring + testing
The service monitor should include: 1-soap connect, 2-wget, 3-pinging host, 4-pinging endpoing

Merge BioCatalogue - Embrace

The merge will happen when all the features in Embrace are implemented in BioCatalogue. 2 left: testing infrastructure and APIs.

SAB minutes?

Thomas will send it to the list.

Annotation model document

Franck & Eric are writing it up.

Progress/developement of the pilot

We had good feedback from the friend list. The beta site is no more password protected.
Jits has produced a page to gather metric information.

Action Items

Eric: update the list on issue related to testing and monitoring

Franck: Create a wiki page for testing and monitoring issues.

Upcoming Meetings

ISMB

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Apr 20 2009

Next meeting:

Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Date: Tuesday 30th September 2008

Time: 15:00-17:00 (UK)

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Carole, Jits, Mike, Paolo

EBI: Eric, Thomas

Apologies

Katy, Hamish, Rodrigo

Minuting

Franck

Agenda

Action from the last telcon.

Report from Eric's last visit.

Progress with the pilot - are we rolling? What is plan B?

Wish list for after the pilot (discuss):

Plugins for myexperiment.

Service testing.

Integration with Taverna.

AOB.

Actions from Previous Meeting

Jits: setup a developer design meeting. Completed

Jits: Speak to Dave about the new privacy policy in myExperiment Ongoing

Everyone: read EBI privacy policy. Ongoing

Jits/Thomas: discuss UI coordination. Completed

Eric/Jits: Agree on a date for Eric's visit in Manchester. Completed

Thomas : Add the questionnaire to the website. It was decided to drop this action as the pilot is weeks away. To Be removed

Minutes

Report from Eric's last visit

Investigated the Taverna WSDL parser for complex type services but did not find it useful for the pilot. It was decided that we'll handle complex type service latter on after the pilot. Eric/Franck/Jits also discussed the handling of services instances. For SOAP services, Service instance will be based on the WSDL location; each instance can have several versions. Annotations of a service instance can apply to multiple version. Eric and Jits did some coding.

Progress with the pilot: are we rolling? What is plan B?

No plan B! We've go to deliver the pilot. At worse delay it. Eric working on the submission piece. Jits looking at updating data model, based on latest disucssions, and looking at service mapping and generation of unique service code which could be used by myExperiment or Taverna to refer to a specific service in the catalogue. Thomas has completed the logging mechanism which required user name and password. He added few changes to the UI.

Support for annotation being very essential for the pilot, Jits will take more time on doing that than the integration to myExperiment. The latter can be scheduled after the pilot.

It will be politically incorrect not to support BioMoby services. We don't have to have the ontology at this stage but they may be a possibility to just get all their services and treat the ontology terms as tags. We can find out if Eddy can help.

Evaluation strategy for the pilot

Mark Wilkinson will be in Manchester so will test it as a provider

We'll advertise or demo the pilot at the Semantic web service in November

Show and tell at the EBI

Show and tell in Manchester

Testing by our PALS and friends.

Continued on: Evaluation strategy for the pilot

Wish list for after the pilot

We need a clear roadmap after the pilot to tell people what to expect next. Some element for the roadmap:

workflow monitor

usage metrics collection

notifications

BioMoby support

Other service type support (Rest…)

Similarity search mechanism

Amazon like search mechanism

Semantic annotation and search mechanism

Continued on: RoadMap

Paolo was more interested in the semantic annotation side of the catalogue. He wanted to know if BioCatalogue will support SAWSDL services. Carole suggested that it should be possible to query the catalogue with a SAWSDL interface.

New Actions

* Gather the Must Could Should Won't requirements (Done: Requirements for Pilot)

Next Meeting

Tues 07/10/2008

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Sept 09 2008

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Oct 7 2008

BioCatalogue Mass Curator

The BioCatalogue Mass Curator application is a small tool which utilizes BioCatalogue's read/write API to handle batch annotation of web services via the use of spreadsheets

BioCatalogue curators can use the tool to browse and/or search the catalogue for web services and select services they are interested in annotating. The selected collection of services can then be exported into an annotation template (in the form of an Excel spreadsheet). Curators can then add different types of annotation to the services within the spreadsheet such as, but not limited to, descriptions, tags, and example data.

Mass Curator currently supports the annotation of SOAP services only; a user can only add annotations to the SOAP service, the SOAP operations, and the SOAP inputs and outputs. REST service support is yet to come.

After adding annotations to the spreadsheet, curators can then use the tool to extract the annotations from the spreadsheet and upload them to the BioCatalogue.

For information on the development of this tool and/or how to build your own Mass Curator instance, visit Mass Curator Development

Getting Started

You can download a copy of Mass Curator from http://github.com/myGrid/BioCatalogue-Mass-Curator/downloads.

Once you have downloaded and extracted the contents of the archive, you can either: double click the BioCatalogue-Mass-Curator.jar file to run the application, * *OR * * open up your command line and enter java -jar BioCatalogue-Mass-Curator.jar

This will run the application with the default configuration options. In the application's directory is a mass-curator.conf file; edit this file to set your own options for Mass Curator.

Configuration Options

The default configuration is:

[application]
biocatalogue-hostname = "http://www.biocatalogue.org"
services-per-page = 15
search-results-per-page = 10

[spreadsheet]
include-help = true

application

biocatalogue-hostname lets you specify which BioCatalogue instance you would like to use for you session. We recommend that you do not use the same exported spreadsheet across different BioCatalogue instances.

services-per-page is a number between 0 and 50 for the number of services to load per page in the main application browser.

search-results-per-page is a number between 0 and 50 for the number of services to load per page the search results browser.

spreadsheet

include-help lets you choose whether to export the “HELP” worksheet along with your selected services or not; this value can either be true or false. Any other value will be intepreted as false

In the event that the application fails to read your config file, the defaults are used.

Date: Monday 30th Mar 2009

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08445805588

Pin: 70503010

Attending

Manchester: Carole, Jits

EBI: Rodrigo, Thomas

Apologies

Franck, Eric, Steve

Minuting

Jits

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

what next after the SAB?

Possible collaboration with Microsoft-meeting with Rudy

Progress/developement of the pilot - are we rolling?

Test infrastructure setup at EBI

Technical meeting

Summary of tasks on rubyForge

BioCatalogue support review

20 Questions analysis

Actions from Previous Meeting

Franck: submit ISMB demo abstract by 20th April… UNKNOWN

Carole: to talk at the BioIT meeting about our policy… ONGOING

Rodrigo: DDBJ, NCBI – ownership and diplomacy… ONGOING

Franck: Sourcing from ontology to be added to the task list… UNKNOWN

Jits: Create a mailing list for the SAB team… ONGOING

Minutes

Previous Actions

Discussed the need to make proper and more comprehensive minutes for the SAB meeting.

We need a set of recommendations post SAB meeting.

What were the key things from the SAB meeting?

Expectation management of users and making sure BioCatalogue does not endorse any metadata that is not professionally curated.

The need for better search clustering, browsing, and faceting is important, which requires more and better classification of services.

Keeping providers in the loop - continual feedback and providing them with the tools to keep on top of things.

Distinguish between subjective and objective opinions and make this VERY CLEAR to users.

NOTE: the above list is only speculative and the final outcomes of the SAB meeting will be confirmed once full minutes are produced.

Discussed what Carole needs to speak about at the BioIT meeting re policies:

Policy for takedown and responsibilities.

Disclaimers.

Which brings the need for users to agree to these policies/disclaimers/conditions on signup.

Discussed the BRO (Biological Resource Ontology?) from MIBBI. Rodrigo: would be useful to speak to them as the have a lot of experience.

We discussed sourcing from ontologies and how we need a much better biologically oriented model of annotations so that we can make discovery of services, especially focusing on inputs, easier and more useful.

Re: annotating inputs - the myGrid ontology has things in it that are important and can be used to start with.

We need to focus our attentions on this data model and get it at a stable and more useful state! (This is the conceptual data model rather than any implementation data model).

Observations about current data model and it's documentation:

We need a “clean” data model showing all possible annotations and on what structures of a service.

There are many missing pieces.

It needs to be biologically-driven - it has to cater for our target domain and target users and provide that added value that only comes from real domain knowledge.

We need a minimum information model + any constrained options for values (eg: annotation with attribute “sequence” can only take the following values “x”, “y”….). This is very much about the Bronze/Silver/Gold/Platinum model, which needs to be revisited and continually evolved.

The documentation is not clear about the whole layered approach - ie: (i) service structures + (ii) generic annotation model + (iii) concrete annotations on the service structures. We need better documentation! Especially for (iii).

Rodrigo proposes that Franck goes down to the EBI for 3 days to work on data model with Eric/Rodrigo/Thomas/Hamish. Unanimous agreement.

Carole has emailed Rudi (MS BioIT guy). Drafting a letter - “memorandum of understanding”. BioCatalogue isn't a legal entity - MoU with project or per institution? Rodrigo: would have to involve EMBLEM, which we don't want to do!

REST API and myExp integration are not of high priority - we need a richly populated + richly featured site first.

Should be move to mod_rails/Passenger? Unanimous agreement.

Upcoming Meetings

Biocuration meeting 16-19 april

ISMB - we have a poster accepted

AOB

Should we change the meeting date?

New Actions

Franck: sort out wording for policies/disclaimers/conditions and figure out a plan on where to put these on the site, and where users need to be notified of these.

Jits: make his notes from the SAB meeting (incl new tasks identified) available.

Rodrigo, Franck: update the SAB minutes and make them more comprehensive minutes.

Carole: ring BBSRC programme manager to inform her that the SAB has taken place and then see what they have to say.

Jits: send example FETA XML files to list, to show an example of what kind of metadata is in them.

Carole: to dig out MS Word + OBOE plugin/tool.

Steve, Eric: provide an update on what is happening with the test scripts execution environment.

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Mar 16 2009

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Apr 07 2009

The BioCatalogue Roadmap for 2010

Please note that the time scales listed are estimated. New requirements and changes driven by the user community may affect features, delivery dates and schedule.

You can access the previous roadmap here: 2009 roadmap

First quarter of 2010 (Jan - Mar)

Public APIs (I) - Basic RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (mainly read).

Service monitoring - testing - Test scripts to test out service functionality can be provided by submitters and service providers. We will then run these regularly to provide us with metrics on the availability/reliability. A traffic light system (red, green, amber) gives users an at-a-glance view on status.

REST services support (II) - Better support for REST services, with the ability to describe and annotate the exact Resources, Methods, Parameters and Representations of REST services.

Service changes monitoring - Monitoring changes in the WSDLs of services and updating the BioCatalogue records and providing a log of changes.

User interface improvements - A revamped operations/inputs/outputs browser to allow easy navigation and annotation of operations/inputs/outputs of services

Second quarter of 2010 (Apr - Jun)

Service ownership - Better management of who the provides a service and which people are maintainers / points of contacts.

Public APIs (II) - More functional RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (read).

Full EMBRACE import : Import all services, metadata, users and test scripts from the EMBRACE registry

REST service annotation improvement Better support for describing REST services - Describe endpoints, parameters and representations

BioCatalogue plugin for Taverna: Alpha version of the BioCatalogue plugin for Taverna 2.1.2

User interface improvement: Improve user interface for browsing SOAP operations and REST endpoints

Search improvement: Possibility to return matching SOAP operations in search

Third quarter 2010 (Jul - Sep)

Annotation Jamboree! (II) at the EMBRACE Workshop for Web Service Providers in Bioinformatics (June 2-4, 2010), Denmark

Curation workbench/tools - New curation tools designed for expert curators.

Major curation of the service providers information in the Catalogue - replace host name by actual service provider name

Integration with Taverna - Ability to import Web Services and annotations to and from BioCatalogue and Taverna.

myBioCatalogue - Ability to set up your own local BioCatalogue registry.

Service Monitoring improvement - Ability to update WSDLs entry in the BioCatalogue

Service ownership - Members may request responsibility for a service

Implement an activity feed for services

Homepage improvement - Activity feed for the homepage

Archiving mechanism for services, operations, inputs and outputs

Search improvement: Return matching REST endpoints in search

Fourth quarter 2010 (Oct - Dec)

API (III): JSON outputs for all API endpoints, Initial Write API and OAuth support for authentication and authorisation through the API

Support for HTTPS (SSL) connections

Service monitoring improvement: Support for SoapUI test suites (xml project files), Show historical success rate of tests and Email notification to users when test status changes

BioCatalogue Taverna plugin (II): New BioCatalogue plugin for Taverna 2.3 with a much more simplified user interface

Curation tools: Mass curation desktop application ( e.g. using spreadsheets for mass curation of services)

The features we plan to implement or improve for 2011 can be found here: roadmap 2011

BioCatalogue Project Kick-Off Meeting

Place : Manchester

Date : 28/29 April 2008

Agenda

Monday 28th April

12.00 Lunch

13.30 Introduction to the meeting: introducing people to each other, their roles – Carole

14.00 Introduction to the project including discussion – Carole (with Rodrigo and Robert joining in)

Brief demo of myExperiment – Jiten Bhagat

15.30 Tea break

16.00 Curation Perspective: Service directories, state of the art for service curation, what we have. what we want

Current myGrid practices: good and evil Franck Tanoh (with Katy joining in)

Bionanny and workflow analytics Alan and Jits

Current state of the art and other initiatives (Hunter, Microsoft, UDDI, SAWSDL, SEEKDA etc) Franck Tanoh (with Katy joining in)

Other similar resources (Strengths and Weaknesses) - Eric Nzuobontane

Web Services Status from the EBI - Hamish

Minimum Information About Open Web Services proposal in submission to the Minimum Information for Biological and Biomedical Investigations (MIBBI) - Duncan Hull http://mibbi.sourceforge.net/

Digitial Library perspective - David De Roure

Discussion with everyone joining in

17.30 Summary of discussion points and replanning for next day

19.00 Pub and Dinner somewhere nice

Tuesday 29th April

09.00 Discovery Perspective: SOTA, what we have and what we want

myExperiment - Jiten Bhagat

EB-eye - Rodrigo Lopez

Feta: an example of what we don't want - Franck

Amazon shopping metaphor - Carole Goble

Other initiatives

Discussion

11.00 Coffee Break

11.30 Project planning

Architecture

Metadata models

Key standards

Supporting the curation pipeline

Low hanging fruit

Key milestones

12.30 Lunch

13.00 Admin niff-naff

Project management methods - f2f, skype chats, wiki, mailing lists

Tying into myExperiment, Taverna and EBI efforts

BBSRC report

Meetings

Collaborations

15.30 FINISH

Attendees

From EBI

Thomas Laurent

Rodrigo Lopez

Hamish McWilliam

Eric Nzuobontane

From Manchester

Jiten Bhagat

Carole Goble

Duncan Hull

Robert Stevens

Franck Tanoh

Alan Williams (for BioNanny part of the meeting)

Kaixuan Wang (Observer)

Katy Wolstencroft

On Skype:

David De Roure / Danius Michaelides

Representative from NBIC

Apologies

Discussions

Day 1

Introductions from attendees

EBI people:

Eric – Web services and back end guy for biocatalogue

Thomas web site – web developer and interfaces experience with bio background

Hamish – data processing pipelines – srs, blast, fasta etc – involved in web service development at ebi. Hamish is main support person.

Rodrigo – head the external services group – gateway for web etc, web services

We need a logo and possibly a new name. Is Biocatalogue ok? Legal problems last time for biocatalogue at the EBI

Introduction to the project

Carole introducing why web services and workflows are important

Not only web services to consider – java, perl, biomart.

Most users are not in big commercial enterprises – consumers and producers could be different – but some people are both

Workflow analytics important for biocatalogue too – as service analytics is a big part

Web services – domain and shim services have different properties and this affects finding and using them

Brief introduction to myExperiment – descriptions of workflows – EMOs – shopping metaphor

Things being looked at and/or adopted by myExperiment (mostly for EMOs) OAI-ORE – model for object reuse and exchange – standard in the library community – W3C community PMH – protocol for metadata harvesting

Annotation commodities

Object

Annotation Model

Functional

Operational

Provenance

Reputation

Descriptions

Ontologies

Controlled vocab

Tags

Folksonomies

Free text

Tagging – how do we over-see the tagging rather than controlling? Do we need more that tags? Is there still a place for ontologies as well? Everyone agreed that not exposing ontologies to users is a good thing – but they could play a role under the hood The important thing is helping users annotate by providing better tooling – keep everything simple – we can’t force people to fill in lots of forms etc. Keeping ahead of our competitors – not competing by being uniquely different – it implies a steep learning curve – users don’t want that. Use metaphors that the customers already know – shopping for airline tickets, for example, is the same whatever company you use.

A Brief Description of other initiatives in the community

UDDI – is it dying? No longer being used by IBM etc. It is being used for things it wasn’t originally designed for.

Annotation swirl – SMARTER curation – Carole’s acronym

Wiki professional – Marco suggested we look at it

Wiki protein – annotation is always connected to a user. If they are an expert, the curation is worth more. Wiki pathway is an extension of this

Rodrigo is worried by wiki protein – no peer review – we need provenance of annotations

MIBBI – set of data types – not services – MIAOWS proposal is therefore different – how would that work? What IS the minimum?

Range of services we need to describe – rest, soap, biomoby – no migration of services.

Hamish talks about web services at the EBI

Domains and technologies mostly bio users but some chemists and systems – see slides

They support REST and SOAP – lots of services have both interfaces

REST – DAS and Http

SeekDa – bioinformatics services feature high in web services cloud

Web services and web interface just as popular according to the ebi graph

Documentation

WSDL documentation – travels with wsdl but are inconsistently done

Good for describing the interface but not the service function usually

Services page

Already got web page docs – to reuse – what’s the api? Methods and data structure

Sample clients – java and perl

Also looking at dotnet

Complex dependencies between parameters – inputs and outputs also

Need to give combinations and ranges of allowed values

Eg blast – protein/nucleotide/db and type of search

Metadata and EB-Eye

Who are your users? Most bench biologists use fill in web forms

Web services – developers writing plugins

Bioinf users doing high throughput – workflows or otherwise

How do we tell users how to use services? How do we stop people doing DOS attacks? Rodrigo told of web service problems and we described similar

Marco suggested that other users’ documentation would be more useful than developers stuff. Rodrigo suggested that sometimes people don’t or can’t read documentation, so we need to control those situations.

* Data is changing all the time and so are the resources – there is a history which needs preserving. Provenance of documentation and annotation very important

In myExp the users are generally the same – small community and self monitoring. All skilled

Alan talks about Bionanny

A web service with rest interface. Can monitor workflows of interest.

Services being not available – where do you monitor that?

Some people set up alternates before runtime – some just want any old alternate that can be found and some will want to stop the workflow until it is back again

Pingers – how do we keep track of services – what is up and working? How does that change with real data?

Should ‘get status’ be part of the minimum information model?

How does this relate to the open provenance model? Does it have a mechanism to report service problems?

Franck talks about current myGrid metadata

We need to remove the annotation tool and start again – Pedro is not suitable. We need a more webby and more dynamic interface. We need to preserve the annotations we already have though, so we need to think about migration

Dave talks about the digital library perspective –

emo and oai-ore protocols

Exchanging metadata about arbitrary objects – harvesting standard – eg used in e-prints, fedora etc.

Focus on object reuse and exchange – still in alpha format. Acknowledged the need to group objects together. In myExp this is the emo – a description of all the different pieces and giving it a URI

myExp is about working with experimental objects/research objects rather than just workflows or services

Day 2

Starts with a myExperiment demo

Thomas asked why there is the option to view but not download and we discussed bio practices of publication and when that could be and why it might be appropriate

Marco brought up the publications store concept – making myExperiment THE place to reference workflows in papers

Biocatalogue is different because it is a registry and not a repository.

Myexperiment is a gossip shop and ‘water cooler’

Tagging important – who tagged what is interesting and should be preserved

Services inside workflows – find out what’s inside – find out when particular services are used

When is an operation different? Jits suggests that if the metadata no longer applies, then it is a new version

Combinations of parameters are important and can be badly selected by users – but we are building this for professionals – they should know a bit about what they are trying to do

Marco brought up web service versions – how do you do this? Hamish said there have been attempts – services contain version numbers – but many service providers do not bother, so it is a hard and unsolved problem

Franck and Eric on state of the art

UDDI – business to business model – flawed and now on the decline. Only useful for WSDL and we have more than that

SeekDa demo – interesting site and already contains a lot of web services. Do we need to collaborate with these people? They suggested it – we need to know their model before we join them – how do they make their money, for example?

serviceFinder is a web 2.0 interface for seekda

EB-Eye – all about searching for data – how does that map to searching for services?

Lumina – wsdl-s and owl-s – all these things change frequently – so Carole advocates not adopting them for now

SAWSDL – w3 recommendation – could become more widely adopted – we should watch its progress. SAWSDL relies on adding to the WSDL file, so it must be the service providers who adopt this. We cannot add sawsdl to existing wsdls without changing their location

Robert asks is there anything that indexes “stuff”, heterogeneous collections of data and resources? Biology links directory – just a web page with links on it

Marco/Robert brought up skos as a search mechanism instead of formal ontologies and we discussed having skos as a search tool and ontology descriptions as mechanisms for knowing how to invoke services

Duncan on MIAOWS

Discussion about the differences between finding and invoking

What does it do is fundamental – and missing from duncan’s model

No provision for data formats or underlying data resources or algorithms. I would add these to the model also

Need examples and mandatory/optional/default. Is this minimum or extra useful stuff?

Project Planning

Workpackages

Wp1 back end catalogue

Wp2 acquisition and discovery

Wp3 discovery tools

Wp4 content acquisition

Wp5 user engagement & community building

Carole proposes moving the api work forward – do a thin slice of some model, some backend and some curation – sooner than six months

Prototyping model and browser – maybe even as a series of power point slides

Rodrigo explained the hardware available – got a sys admin to set up environment for working – franck, jits and eric need to work out what they need

Biocatalogue will be set up in ebi and interface myExperiment as well as lots of other applications

What should we start with? Thomas suggested – clicking on a service and going to biocatalogue interface – maybe as an advanced feature, we could skin it so it looks like myExperiment

Migrate descriptions from Feta and EB-Eye

Would we have time for tagging? What is the tagging bus between myExp and biocat?

Simple biocatalogue

Minimal service model

Programming interface

Skinning with myExperiment

Migrate feta

Migrate ebi descriptions

Rodrigo suggests by next Friday that we have mock ups and proposals for simple models

Do we need to consider the curation model?

Nominate your services – 12 or so – representative of range – and used in workflows. Eric and Franck and me

write a simple schema Eric and Franck and me

Thomas and Rodrigo to do interface mock-ups

User type – mapping

Documentation, wiki etc – Carole, Jits

Set up techy show and tell - jits

Document the meeting – Robert and carole writing a briefings paper about annotating web services

Set up techy show and tell backends

Tuesday 13 May 4-5 pm planning – telecon?

In detail…..

Infrastructure:

Domain name (EBI)

Hardware (EBI)

Infrastructure development

Jits + Eric

understanding myExp infrastructure

Understanding the myExp model

M1 (throwaway):

Simple biocatalogue

Minimal service model

Programming interface

'Skinning' with myExp

Migrate Feta (myGrid)

Migrate EBI description

(tagging)

Tag service? Tag bus?

Write up stories by May For Tuesday 13th May, 4pm - 5pm Data show and tell

Simple schema (Eric & Franck, Katy cheering)

Thomas, Rodrigo mock up (Thomas)

Nominate your services (Franck)

12 services

Annotated

Representative of range

In workflows

User types (Hamish)

Documentation / Notes from meeting / Wiki / Slides (Carole & Jits)

Set up techy show + tell (myexperiment stuff) (Jits & Eric)

Create new mailing list

Create a new space on dev wiki

Action Items

Others

Codebase Testing

After the ISMB release of the BioCatalogue codebase, it is crucial that we have in place a systematic way of working with to the codebase in order to manage growth and development. Part of this is about having a disciplined development process but equally this requires a comprehensive suite of automated tests to test various aspects of the codebase.

Things to Test

WSDL parsing

Service submission

User management:

Registration

Change password

Search

Event logging

Tools

(ones in bold are the ones we use)

Factory Girl

Shoulda

Running Tests

Install the necessary development gems.

Create a test database.

Configure the test environment in config/database.yml to use this test db.

Run all tests:

rake

OR

rake test

To run unit tests or functional tests only:

rake test:units

rake test:functional

To run a specific test, an example:

rake test:units TEST=test/unit/lib/bio_catalogue/tags_test.rb

NOTE: when running individual tests - errors can occur whilst running “rake test” that you don't get when running the individual test that contains the errors. Thus there might be errors on the individual test that only show up when ALL tests are run. Therefore, ensure that you run all tests as a final check.

This page is now deprecated. Please do not update!

General Info on Web Services

What are Web Services?

Web Service is a resource that can be programatically accessed over the Internet. The difference between Web Services and Web Servers is that Web Servers concentrate on user interface which is displayed in a browser and accessible to humans, whereas Web Services concentrate on execution by programs or scripts.

This does not mean that Web Services cannot be executed by humans. Contrary, there are many tools that automatically generate graphical interfaces for Web Services, which saves time spent on building the interface by service providers.

Why should I use Web Services or turn my resources into Web Services?

There are many advantages on using web services:

Web Services are easy to execute: Once you've set up a Web Service, you can execute them by various tools that will automatically generate the input forms and display the results. You can also incorporate the service in any code in any programming language in any place in the World without the need of program installation. Finally, you can use several services in one analysis by incorporate Web Services into pipelining systems. For details see: Help on executing Web Serices

Web Services are easy to create: There are easy-to-use state of art tools for making services out of websites, command line applications and functions in any of commonly used programming languages, for details look at Help on creating Web Services

Web Services are easy to publish: You don't have to worry how to make your service visible to the public. After registering them in a popular public repository such as BioCatalogue makes it easy to find based on its type, category, location, descriptions, tags, input type etc. BioCatalogue will parse and expose your automatically generated service documentation stored in a WSDL file. Moreover, you will benefit from curated community support while maintaining the possibility of adding descriptions and example data in the future.

Different types of web services

There are different types of web services:

SOAP:

REST:

Soaplab: specific type of SOAP services developed by EBI

20 Questions for BioCatalogue

(ref: Jim Gray's 20 Questions [link])

Similar to what is happening for myExperiment

We have identified 4 categories of questions so far

1- questions on statistics in the system, how many…

How many services has provider X? …currently implemented but need to make sure it clear enough for users… How many of those are REST? How many of those are SOAP? …different type of services should be clear on the site and users should know the number of each type after a search… implemented

How many submitters does provider X have?…number of submitter from a provider must be clear

How many services are annotated at bronze, silver, gold and platinum standards? … should be possible to filter service using the different level of annotation.

2- questions on metrics, status

What is the reliability profile of service X? Can I see the usage history of service X? who is the provider? is it free… Each service should have a profile (reliability, history of use, free, licenses etc)

Which are the most recently updated services? Which are the most recently registered services? Most search services? …possibility to filter services based on these factors.

3- questions about relations/functions of services (this section requires rich annotations)

Which services consume given input/output?… possible if we have a semantic annotation in place

Which service takes input X and generates output Y (under conditions x,y, z)?

Which services perform a given biological function?

Which service can I use in place of a given service?

Which other service is using the same data as service X?

What paper(DOI) or myExperiment workflows are available for this service?… possibility to point to external resources for service description.

4-housekeeping questions

The questions here are about:

A- How to use BioCatalogue

How do I report misinformation in the registry? … how can users contact us?…ongoing

Can i access the catalogue in any other way? … use our code/APIs …ongoing

What 'functions' are available? … list of thing user can do

Will my account be deactivated, after some period(how long?) of inactivity?

Do I have to register?… justify the need for registration for service submission

Who do I contact for more information about service X?… internal messaging.

B- Capability

Can I filter tags by service, operation, parameters? can I find operations?

Do I have access to the output in JSON and/or RDF/XML, SAWSDL …

Are there any restrictions in the number of calls I an make?

C- Sustainability

Who are you? … who is behind BioCatalogue

Will you be around next year time? …

How can I get involved in BioCatalogue? …